<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hays-mec">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="statusBar">The Memoirs of Emma Courtney</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Mary</forename>
                    <surname>Hays</surname>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Tonya Howe</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of <title>The Novels in Context</title> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study
               and the teaching of the eighteenth-century development of the novel in English.</p>
                <p>
                    <normalization>
                    Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded. Hyphenation has not been retained. </normalization>
                </p>
                <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions. 
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed for G. G. and J. Robinson, Paternoster-Row</publisher>
                    <date type="firstEd">1796</date>
                    <extent type="physical">2v. ; 12⁰</extent>
                    <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7">Pages 1-7</biblScope>
                    <note>This item is located in the Library of Congress.</note>
                </imprint>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Public domain electronic facsimile copy</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Google eBook</publisher>
                    <date type="accessed">18 August 2014</date>
                    <extent type="online">http://books.google.com/books?id=94UgAAAAMAAJ</extent>
                </imprint>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <epigraph xml:lang="en">
                <cit>
                    <bibl>Rousseau</bibl>
                    <quote>
                        <l>
                        The preceptions of persons in retirement are very
                  different from those of people in the great world: their passions, being
                  differendy modified, are differently expressed; their imaginations, constantly
                  impressed by the same objects, are more violently affected. The same small number
                  of images continually return, mix with every idea, and create those strange and
                  false notions, so remarkable in people who spend their lives in solitude.</l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
            </epigraph>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>
                <span title="thesis" class="mark">
                    <span class="mark" title="valueClaim">The most interesting, and the most useful, fictions,
                  are, perhaps, such, as delineating the progress, and tracing the consequences, of
                  one strong, indulged, passion, or prejudice, afford materials, by which the
                  philosopher may calculate the powers of the human mind, and learn the springs
                  which set it in motion</span>
                </span>—<span class="mark" title="quote">
                    <rs type="treatise" ref="TM2">'Understanding, and talents,' says <rs type="person" ref="HEL">Helvetius</rs>, 'being nothing more, in men, than the produce of their
                     desires, and particular situations.'</rs>
                </span>
                <span class="mark" title="gothic">Of the passion of terror <span class="mark" title="allusion">
                        <rs type="person" ref="AR">Mrs Radcliffe</rs>
                    </span> has made admirable use in her ingenious romances.</span>—In
               the novel of <rs type="title" ref="CW">Caleb Williams</rs>, <span class="mark" title="character">curiosity in the hero,
               and the love of reputation in the soul-moving character of Falkland, fostered into
               ruling passions</span>, are drawn with a masterly hand.</p>
            <p>
                For the subject of these Memoirs, a more universal
                  sentiment is chosen—a sentiment hackneyed in this species of composition,
                  consequently more difficult to treat with any degree of originality;—yet, <span class="mark" title="purpose">to
                  accomplish this, has been the aim of the author</span>; with what success, the public
                  will, probably, determine.
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="valueClaim">Every writer who advances principles, whether
                  true or false, that have a tendency to set the mind in motion, does good.</span>
               Innumerable mistakes have been made, both moral and philosophical:—while covered with
                  <span class="mark" title="religion">a sacred and mysterious veil</span>, how are
               they to be detected? <span class="mark" title="science">From various combinations and
                  multiplied experiments, truth, only, can result.</span>
                <span class="mark" title="reason">Free thinking, and free
               speaking, are the virtue and the characteristics of a rational being</span>:—there can be no
               argument which mitigates against them in one instance, but what equally mitigates
               against them in all; <span class="mark" title="religion">
                    <span class="mark" title="science">
                        <span class="mark" title="experience">every principle must be doubted, before it will be
                     examined and proved.</span>
                    </span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="purpose" type="negative">
                    <span class="mark" title="romance">It has commonly been the business
                  of fiction to pourtray characters, not as they really exist, but, as, we are told,
                  they ought to be—a sort of ideal perfection, in which nature and passion are
                  melted away, and jarring attributes wonderfully combined.</span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="character">In delineating the character of Emma Courtney, I had not in view these fantastic
               models: <span class="mark" title="realism">
                        <span class="mark" title="purpose">I meant
                     to represent her, as a human being, loving virtue while enslaved by passion,
                     liable to the mistakes and weaknesses of our fragile
                  nature</span>
                    </span>
                </span>.—<span class="mark" title="reader">Let those readers, who feel
                  inclined to judge with severity the extravagance and eccentricity of her conduct,
                  look into their own hearts</span>; and should they there find no record, traced by an
                  accusing spirit, to soften the asperity of their censures—yet, let them bear in
                  mind, that the errors of my heroine were the offspring of sensibility; and that
                     <span class="mark" title="science">
                    <span class="mark" title="experience">the result of her hazardous experiment</span>
                </span>
                  is calculated to operate as <span class="mark" title="purpose">a&#160;warning, rather
                     than as an example.</span>—The philosopher—who is not ignorant, that
               light and shade are more powerfully contrasted in minds rising above the common
               level; that, <span class="mark" title="metaphor">as rank weeds take strong root in a fertile soil, vigorous powers not
               unfrequently produce fatal mistakes and pernicious exertions</span>; that <span class="mark" title="character">character is the
               produce of a lively and constant affection</span>—may, possibly, <span class="mark" title="purpose">discover in these Memoirs
                  traces of reflection, and of some attention to the phænomena of the human mind</span>.</p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="probability">Whether the incidents, or the characters, are
                  copied from life, is of little importance—The only question is, if
                  the&#160;circumstances, and situations, are altogether improbable?</span> If
               not—<span class="mark" title="logic">whether the consequences&#160;might&#160;not have followed from the circumstances?</span>—<span class="mark" title="valueClaim">This is
               a grand question, applicable to all the purposes of education, morals, and
               legislation</span>—and on this I rest my moral—<span class="mark" title="quote">
                    <rs type="biblical" ref="MTW">'Do men gather figs of thorns, or grapes of
               thistles?' asked a moralist and a reformer</rs>
                </span>.</p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="probability">Every&#160;possible&#160;incident, in works of this
                  nature, might, perhaps, be rendered&#160;probable, <span class="mark" title="editorial.xml#connection">were a sufficient regard paid to the
                  more minute, delicate, and connecting links of the chain</span>.</span> Under this
               impression, I chose, as the least arduous, a simple story—and, even in that, the fear
               of repetition, of prolixity, added, it may be, to a portion of indolence, made me, in
               some parts, neglectful of this rule:—yet, in tracing the character of my heroine from
               her birth, I had it in view. For the conduct of my hero, I consider myself less
               responsible—it was not&#160;his&#160;memoirs that I professed to write.</p>
            <p> I am not sanguine respecting the success of this little publication. <span class="mark" title="gothic">It is truly observed, by <rs type="person" ref="MGL">the writer of <rs type="novel" ref="MONK">a late popular novel</rs>
                    </rs>—<span class="mark" title="quote">'That an author, whether good or bad, or between
                     both, is an animal whom every body is privileged to attack; for, though all are
                     not able to write books, all conceive themselves able to judge them. A bad
                     composition carries with it its own punishment—contempt and ridicule:—a good
                     one excites envy, and (frequently) entails upon its author a thousand
                     mortifications.'</span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span class="mark" title="affect">
                    <span class="mark" title="reason">
                        <span class="mark" title="reader">To the feeling and the thinking few</span>, this
                     production of an active mind, in a season of impression, rather than of
                     leisure, is presented.</span>
                </span>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>