<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet href="style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>  --><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="file:/C:/Users/Tonya/Dropbox/DHOXSS%202013/NiC-not%20in%20use/style.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="more-femed">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="statusBar">Strictures on the Modern System of Female Education</title>
                <author>
                    <person xml:id="HM" sex="F" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hannah_More">
                        <forename>Hannah</forename>
                        <surname>More</surname>
                        <birth when="1745-02-02">2 February 1745</birth>
                        <death when="1833-09-07">7 September 1833</death>
                        <occupation>Writer</occupation>
                        <occupation>Playwright</occupation>
                        <occupation>Philanthropist</occupation>
                        <trait type="Marital Status">Unmarried</trait>
                        <nationality>English</nationality>
                    </person>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Tonya Howe</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of <title>The Novels in Context</title> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study
               and the teaching of the eighteenth-century development of the novel in English.</p>
                <p>
                    <normalization>
                    Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded. Hyphenation has not been retained. </normalization>
                </p>
                <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions. 
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed for T. Cadell Jun. and W. Davies in the Strand</publisher>
                    <date type="firstEd">1799</date>
                    <extent type="physical">2v. ;  8⁰.</extent>
                    <biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="34">Pages</biblScope>
                    <note>First edition.</note>
                    <note>This object is in the Library of Congress.</note>
                </imprint>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Public domain electronic facsimile copy</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>University of Michigan ECCO-TCP</publisher>
                    <extent type="online">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/ecco?c=ecco;iel=4;view=toc;idno=004902140.0001.001</extent>
                </imprint>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>CHAP. VII. On female study, and initiation into knowledge.—Error of cultivating the imagination to the neglect of the judgment.—Books of reasoning recommended.</head>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#purpose">As this little work by no means assumes the
                  character of a general scheme of education, the author has purposely avoided
                  expatiating largely on any kind of instruction; but so far as <span ana="editorial.xml#religion">it is connected, either immediately or remotely,
                     with objects of a moral or religious nature</span>.</span> Of course she has
               been so far from thinking it necessary to enter into the enumeration of those books
               which are useful in general instruction, that she has forborne to mention any. With
               such books <span ana="editorial.xml#youth">the rising generation</span> is far more
               copiously and ably furnished than any preceding period has <pb n="155"/> been; and
               out of an excellent variety <span ana="editorial.xml#distinction">the judicious
                  instructor can hardly fail to make such a selection</span> as shall be beneficial
               to the pupil.</p>
            <p> But while due praise ought not to be withheld from the improved methods of
               communicating the elements of general knowledge; yet is there not some danger that
               our very advantages may lead us into error, by causing us to repose so confidently on
               the multiplied helps which facilitate the entrance into learning, as to render <span ana="editorial.xml#youth">our pupils</span> superficial through the very facility
               of acquirement? <span ana="editorial.xml#education">Where so much is done for them,
                  may they not be led to do too little for themselves? May there not be a moral
                  disadvantage in possessing them with the notion that learning may be acquired
                  without diligence and labour?</span> Sound education never can be made a <span ana="editorial.xml#quote">
                    <rs ref="SKSP">"primrose path of dalliance."</rs>
                </span>
               Do what we will <span ana="editorial.xml#youth">we cannot cheat children into
                  learning or play them into knowledge, according to the smoothness of the modern
                     <pb n="156"/> creed</span>. There is no idle way to any acquisitions which
               really deserve the name. <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor">And as Euclid, in order
                  to repress the impetuous vanity of greatness, told his Sovereign that there was no
                  royal way to geometry, so the fond mother may be assured that there is no short
                  cut to any other kind of learning.</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#religion">The tree of knowledge, as a punishment perhaps,
                  for its having been at first unfairly tasted, cannot now be climbed without
                  difficulty</span>; and this very circumstance serves afterwards to furnish not
               only literary pleasures, but moral advantages: for <span ana="editorial.xml#valueClaim">the knowledge which is acquired by unwearied
                  assiduity is lasting in the possession, and sweet to the possessor; both perhaps
                  in proportion to the cost and labour of the acquisition</span>. And though an able
               teacher ought to endeavour, by improving the communicating faculty in himself, (for
               many know what they cannot teach,) to soften every difficulty; yet in spite of the
               kindness and ability with which he will smooth every <pb n="157"/> obstruction, it is
               probably, among the wise institutions of Providence, that great difficulties should
               still remain. <span ana="editorial.xml#religion">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="religious">For education is but an initiation into that life of trial to
                     which we are introduced on our entrance into this world. It is the first
                     breaking-in to that state of toil and labour to which we are born; and in this
                     view of the subject the acquisition of learning may be converted to higher uses
                     than such as are purely literary.</span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>Will it not be ascribed to a captious singularity if I venture to remark that <span ana="editorial.xml#valueClaim">real knowledge and real piety, though they have
                  gained in many instances, have suffered in others from that profusion of <span ana="editorial.xml#term">little, amusing, sentimental books with which the
                     youthful library overflows</span>
                </span>? <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">Abundance has its dangers as well as scarcity.</span> In the first place may not
               the multiplicity of <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#term">these alluring little works</span>
                </span> increase the natural reluctance to
               those more dry and uninteresting studies, of which after all, the rudiments of every
                  <pb n="158"/> part of learning must consist? And, secondly, <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">is there not some danger (though there are many
                  honourable exceptions) that some of those engaging narratives may serve to infuse
                  into the youthful heart a sort of spurious goodness, a confidence of
                  virtue?</span> And that the benevolent actions with the recital of which they
               abound, <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">when they are not made to flow from any
                  source but feeling</span>, may tend to inspire self-complacency, a
               self-gratulation, a "stand by, for I am holier than "thou?" <span ana="editorial.xml#religion">May they not help to infuse a love of popularity and
                  an anxiety for praise, in the place of that simple and unostentatious rule of
                  doing whatever good we do, because it is the will of God?</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#valueClaim">The universal substitution of this principle
                  would tend to purify the worldly morality of many a popular little story.</span>
               And there are few dangers which good parents will more carefully guard against than
               that of giving their children a mere political piety; that sort of religion which
               just goes to make <pb n="159"/> people more respectable, and to stand well with the
               world *.</p>
            <p> There is a certain precocity of mind which is much helped on by these superficial
               modes of instruction; for frivolous reading will produce its correspondent effect, in
               much less time than books of solid instruction; <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">the
                  imagination being liable to be worked upon, and the feelings to be set a going,
                  much faster than the understanding can be opened and the judgment
                  enlightened</span>. <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="religious">A talent
                  for conversation should be the result of education, not its precursor; it is a
                  golden fruit when suffered to ripen gradually on the tree of knowledge; but if
                  forced in the <pb n="160"/> hot-bed of a circulating library, it will turn out
                  worthless and vapid in proportion as it was artificial and premature.</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#youth">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">Girls who have been
                     accustomed to devour frivolous books, will converse and write with a far
                     greater appearance of skill as to style and sentiment at twelve or fourteen
                     years old, than those of a more advanced age who are under the discipline of
                     severer studies; but the former having early attained to that low standard
                     which had been held out to them, became stationary; while the latter, quietly
                     progressive, are passing through just gradations to a higher strain of mind;
                     and those who early begin with talking and writing like women, commonly end
                     with thinking and acting like children.</span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#thesis">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#distinction">The swarms of
                     Abridgments, Beauties, aud Compendiums</span>, which form too considerable a
                  part of a young lady's library, may be considered in many instances as an
                  infallible receipt for making a superficial mind.</span> The names of the renowned
               characters <pb n="161"/> in history thus become familiar in the mouths of those who
               can neither attach to the idea of the person, the series of his actions, nor the
               peculiarities of his character. <span ana="editorial.xml#distinction">A few fine
                  passages from the poets (passages perhaps which derived their chief beauty from
                  their position and connection) are huddled together by some extract-maker</span>,
               whose <span ana="editorial.xml#connection">brief and disconnected patches of broken
                  and discordant materials</span>, while they <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">inflame young readers with the vanity of reciting</span>, neither fill the mind
               nor form the taste: and it is not difficult to trace back to their shallow sources
               the <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">hackney'd quotations</span> of certain
               accomplished young ladies, who will be frequently found not to have come legitimately
               by any thing they know: I mean, not to have drawn it from its true spring, the
               original works of the author from which some beauty-monger has severed it. <span ana="editorial.xml#humanNature">Human inconsistency in this, as in other cases,
                  wants to combine two irreconcileable things; it strives to unite the reputation
                     <pb n="162"/> of knowledge with the pleasures of idleness, forgetting that
                  nothing that is valuable can be obtained without sacrifices, and that if we would
                  purchase knowledge we must pay for it the fair and lawful price of time and
                  industry.</span>
            </p>
            <p> This remark is by no means of general application; there are many valuable works
               which from their bulk would be almost inaccessible to a great number of readers, and
               a considerable part of which may not be generally useful. Even in the best written
               books there is often superfluous matter; authors are apt to get enamoured of their
               subject, and to dwell too long on it: every person cannot find time to read a longer
               work on any subject, and yet it may be well for them to know something on almost
               every subject; <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">those therefore, who abridge
                  voluminous works judiciously, render service to the community</span>. But there
               seems, if I may venture the remark, to be a mistake in the use of abridgments. <span ana="editorial.xml#youth">They are put systematically <pb n="163"/> into the hands
                  of youth, who have, or ought to have leisure for the works at large</span>; while
               abridgments seem more immediately calculated for persons in more advanced life, who
               wish to recal something they had forgotten; who want to restore old ideas rather than
               acquire new ones; or they are useful for persons immersed in the business of the
               world who have little leisure for voluminous reading. They are excellent to refresh
               the mind, but not competent to form it.</p>
            <p>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="medical">Perhaps there is some analogy
                  between the mental and bodily conformation of women. The instructor therefore
                  should imitate the physician. If the latter prescribe bracing medicines for <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">a body of which delicacy is the disease, the former
                     would do well to prohibit relaxing reading for a mind which is already of too
                     soft a texture, and should strengthen its feeble tone by invigorating
                     reading</span>.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">By softness, I cannot be supposed to mean imbecility
                  of understanding, but <pb n="164"/> natural softness of heart, with that indolence
                  of spirit which is fostered by indulging in <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">seducing books</span> and in the general habits of fashionable
               life.</span>
            </p>
            <p> I mean not here to recommend books which are immediately religious, but <span ana="editorial.xml#reason">such as exercise the reasoning faculties</span>, teach
               the mind to get acquainted with its own nature, and to stir up its own powers. <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="alimentary">Let not a timid young lady start if
                  I should venture to recommend to her, after a proper course of preparation, to
                  swallow and digest such strong meat, as Watts's or Duncan's little book of Logic,
                  some parts of Mr. Locke's Essay on the Human Understanding, and Bishop Butler's
                  Analogy.</span> Where there is leisure, and capacity, and an able counsellor,
               works of this nature might be profitably substituted in the place of so much English
               Sentiment, French Philosophy, Italian Poetry, and fantastic German imagery and magic
               wonders. While such enervating or absurd books sadly disqualify the reader for <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">solid pursuit or vigorous <pb n="165"/>
               thinking</span>, the studies here recommended <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="medical">would act upon the constitution of the mind as a kind of
                  alterative, and, if I may be allowed the expression, would help to brace the
                  intellectual stamina</span>.</p>
            <p> This is however by no means intended to exclude works of taste and imagination,
               which must always make <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">the ornamental part, and of
                  course a very considerable part of female studies</span>. It is only suggested
               that they should not form them entirely. For <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="physical">what is called dry tough reading, independent of the knowledge it
                  conveys, is useful as an habit and wholesome as an exercise</span>. Serious study
               serves to harden the mind for more trying conflicts; it lifts the reader from
               sensation to intellect; it abstracts her from the world and its vanities; it fixes a
               wandering spirit, and fortifies a weak one; it divorces her from matter; it corrects
                  <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">that spirit of trifling which she naturally
                  contracts from the frivolous turn of female conversation, <pb n="166"/> and the
                  petty nature of female employments</span>; it concentrates her attention, assists
               her in a habit of excluding trivial thoughts, and thus even helps to qualify her for
               religious pursuits. <span ana="editorial.xml#thesis">Yes; I repeat it, there is to
                  woman a Christian use to be made of sober studies; while books of an opposite
                  cast, however unexceptionable they may be sometimes found in point of expression;
                  however free from evil in its more gross and palpable shapes, yet by their very
                  nature and constitution <span ana="editorial.xml#affect">they excite a spirit of
                     relaxation, by exhibiting scenes and ideas which soften the mind; they impair
                     its general powers of resistance, and at best feed habits of improper
                     indulgence, and nourish a vain and visionary indolence, which lays the mind
                     open to error and the heart to seduction.</span>
                </span>
            </p>
            <p>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">Women are little accustomed to close reasoning on
                  any subject</span>; <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">still less do they inure
                  their minds to consider particular <pb n="167"/> parts of a subject; they are not
                  habituated to turn a truth round and view it in all its varied aspects and
                  positions</span>; and this perhaps is one cause (as will be observed in another *
               place) of the too great confidence they are disposed to place in their opinions.
                  <span ana="editorial.xml#gender">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#imagination">Though
                     their imagination is already too lively</span>, and <span ana="editorial.xml#reason">their judgment naturally incorrect</span>; in
                  educating them we go on to stimulate the imagination, while we neglect the
                  regulation of the judgment.</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="nautical">They already want ballast, and we
                  make their education consist in continually crowding more sail than they can
                  carry.</span> Their intellectual powers being so little strengthened by exercise,
               makes every little business appear a hardship to them: whereas serious study would be
               useful, were it only that it leads the mind to the habit of conquering difficulties.
               But it is peculiarly hard to turn at once from <pb n="168"/> the indolent repose of
               light reading, from the concerns of mere animal life, the objects of sense, or the
               frivolousness of chit chat; it is peculiarly hard, I say, to a mind so softened, to
               rescue itself from the dominion of self-indulgence, to resume its powers, to call
               home its scattered strength, to shut out every foreign intrusion, to force back a
               spring so unnaturally bent, and to devote itself to religious reading, reflection, or
               self-examination: whereas to an intellect accustomed to think at all the difficulty
               of thinking seriously is obviously lessened.</p>
            <p> Far be it from me to desire to make scholastic ladies or female dialecticians; but
               there is little fear that the kind of books here recommended, if thoroughly studied,
               and not superficially skimmed, will make them pedants or induce conceit; for by
               shewing them the possible powers of the human mind, you will bring them to see the
               littleness of their own, and to <pb n="169"/> get acquainted with the mind and to
               regulate it, does not seem the way to puff it up. But let her who is disposed to be
               elated with her literary acquisitions, check her vanity by calling to mind the just
               remark of <rs type="person" ref="SW">Swift</rs>, <quote>that after all her boasted
                  acquirements, a woman will, generally speaking, be found to possess less of what
                  is called learning than a common school-boy.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is there any fear that this sort of reading will convert ladies into authors.
               The direct contrary effect will be likely to be produced by the perusal of writers
               who throw the generality of readers at such an unapproachable distance. <span ana="editorial.xml#writing">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="reproductive">Who are those ever multiplying authors, that with unparalleled fecundity are
                     overstocking the world with their quick succeeding progeny? They are novel
                     writers; the easiness of whose productions is at once the cause of their own
                     fruitfulness, and of the almost infinitely numerous race of imitators to <pb n="170"/> whom they give birth</span>.</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#writing">Such is the frightful facility of this species of
                  composition, that every raw girl while she reads, is tempted to fancy that she can
                  also write.</span> And as Alexander, on perusing the Iliad, found by congenial
               sympathy the image of Achilles in his own ardent soul, and felt himself the hero he
               was studying; and <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="satiric">as Corregio, on
                  first beholding a picture which exhibited the perfection of the Graphic art,
                  prophetically felt all his own future greatness, and cried out in rapture, "And I
                  too am a painter!" so a thorough paced novel reading Miss, at the close of every
                  tissue of hackney'd adventures, feels within herself the stirring impulse of
                  corresponding genius, and triumphantly exclaims, "And I too am an author!—"</span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#metaphor" type="alimentary">The glutted imagination</span>
               soon overflows with the redundance of cheap sentiment and plentiful incident, and by
               a sort of arithmetical proportion, is enabled by the perusal of any three <pb n="171"/> novels to produce a fourth; till every fresh production, like the progeny of <rs type="character" ref="SKSP">Banquo</rs>, is followed by <span ana="editorial.xml#quote">Another, and another, and another</span> * <span ana="editorial.xml#writing">Is a lady, however destitute of talents, education, or
                  knowledge of the world, whose studies have been completed by a circulating
                  library, in any distress of mind? the writing a novel suggests itself as the best
                  soother of her sorrows! <span ana="editorial.xml#economy">Does she labour under
                     any depression of circumstances? writing a novel occurs as the readiest receipt
                     for mending them!</span>
                </span>
                <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">
                    <span ana="editorial.xml#economy">And she
                     solaces herself with the conviction that <pb n="172"/> the subscription which
                     has been given to her importunity or her necessities, has been given to her
                     genius.</span> And this confidence instantly levies a fresh contribution for a
                  succeeding work</span>. <span ana="editorial.xml#economy">Capacity and cultivation
                  are so little taken into the account, that writing a book seems to be now
                  considered as the only sure resource which the idle and the illiterate have always
                  in their power.</span>
            </p>
            <p> May I be indulged in a short digression to remark, though rather out of its place,
               that <span ana="editorial.xml#economy">the corruption occasioned by these books has
                  spread so wide, and descended so low, that not only among milleners,
                  mantua-makers, and other trades where numbers work together, the labour of one
                  girl is frequently sacrificed that she may be spared to read those mischievous
                  books to the others</span>; but the Author has been assured by clergymen, who have
               witnessed the fact, that <span ana="editorial.xml#class">they are procured and
                  greedily read in the wards of our Hospitals! an awful hint, that those who <pb n="173"/> teach the poor to read, should not only take care to furnish them
                  with principles which will lead them to abhor corrupt books, but should also
                  furnish them with such books as shall strengthen and confirm their
                  principles</span> *. <span ana="editorial.xml#religion">And let every Christian
                  remember, that there is no other way of entering truly into the spirit of that
                  divine prayer, which petitions that the name of God may be "hallowed," that <span ana="editorial.xml#reference" type="biblical">his kingdom (of grace) may
                     come,</span> and that <span ana="editorial.xml#reference" type="biblical">his
                     will may be done on earth as it <pb n="174"/> is in heaven,</span> than by each
                  individual contributing according to his measure to accomplish the work for which
                  he prays; for <span ana="editorial.xml#distinguish">to pray that these great
                     objects may be promoted, without contributing to their promotion, is a palpable
                     inconsistency</span>
                </span>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>