<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="smollett-rr">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="statusBar">The Adventures of Roderick Random</title>
                <author>
                    <forename>Tobias</forename>
                    <surname>Smollett</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <surname>Anonymous</surname>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and correction</resp>
                    <name>Elizabeth Ricketts</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Tonya Howe</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This text is prepared as part of <title>The Novels in Context</title> project, which provides an accessible, curated, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study
               and the teaching of the eighteenth-century development of the novel in English.</p>
                <p>
                    <normalization>
                    Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded. Hyphenation has not been retained. </normalization>
                </p>
                <p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions. 
                </p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed for J. Osborn, in Pater-Noster-Row</publisher>
                    <date type="firstEd">1748</date>
                    <extent type="physical">2v. ;  12⁰.</extent>
                    <note>First edition.</note>
                </imprint>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Public domain electronic facsimile copy</pubPlace>
                    <publisher> Internet Archive</publisher>
                    <date type="accessed">24 October 2014</date>
                    <extent type="online">https://archive.org/details/adventuresroder00unkngoog</extent>
                    <note>Sixth edition.</note>
                    <note>This electronic version is a digitization of the sixth edition, housed at the University of Lausanne</note>
                </imprint>
                <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Printed for W. Strachan, J. Rivington, R. Baldwin, Hawes, Clarke, and Collins, W. Johnston, [and 5 others]</publisher>
                    <date>1775</date>
                    <extent type="physical">2v.,plates ;  12⁰.</extent>
                    <note>Tenth edition.</note>
                    <note>The page images are sourced from this object, courtesy of the Library of Congress, Washington DC.</note>
                </imprint>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head type="section">Preface.</head>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb facs="smollett.jpg"/>
            <pb facs="smollett-001.jpg"/>
            <pb facs="smollett-002.jpg"/>
            <p>Of all kinds of satire, there is none so entertaining and universally improving, as that which is introduced, as it were, occasionally, in the course of an interesting story, which brings every incident home to life; and by representing familiar scenes in an uncommon and amusing point of view, invests them with all the graces of novelty, while nature is appealed to in every particular. </p>
            <p>
The reader gratifies his curiosity, in pursuing the adventures of a person in whose favour he is prepossessed; he espouses his cause, he sympathises with him in his distress, his indignation is heated against the authors of his calamity; the humane passions are inflamed; the contrast between dejected virtue, and insulting vice, appears with greater aggravation, and every impression having a double force on the imagination, the memory retains the circumstance, and the heart improves by the example. The attention is not tired with a bare catalogue of characters, but agreeably diverted with all the variety of invention; and the vicissitudes of life appear in their peculiar circumstances, opening an ample field for wit and humour.</p>
            <p>
Romance, no doubt, owes its origin to ignorance, vanity, and superstition. In the dark ages of the World, when a man had rendered himself famous for wisdom or valour, his family and adherents availed themselves of his superior qualities, magnified his virtues, and represented his character and person as sacred and supernatural. The vulgar easily swallowed the bait, implored his protection, and yielded the tribute of homage and praise even to adoration: his exploits were handed down to posterity with a thousand exaggerations; they were repeated as incitements to virtue; divine honours were paid, and altars erected to his memory, for the encouragement of those who attempted to imitate his example; and hence arose the heathen mythology, which is no other than a collection of extravagant romances. - As learning advanced, and genius received cultivation, these stories were embellished with the graces of poetry, that they might the better recommend themselves to the attention; they were sung in public, at festivals, for the instruction and delight of the audience; and rehearsed before battle, as incentives to deeds of glory. Thus tragedy and the epic muse were born, and, in the progress of taste, arrived at perfection. - It is no wonder that the ancients could not relish a fable in prose, after they had seen so many remarkable events celebrated in verse, by their best poets; we therefore find no romance among them, during the era of their excellence, unless the Cyropaedia of Xenophon may be so called; and it was not till arts and sciences began to revive, after the irruption of the Barbarians into Europe, that any thing of this kind appeared. But when the minds of men were debauched by the imposition of priest-craft to the most absurd pitch of credulity; the authors of romance arose, and losing sight of probability, filled their performances with the most monstrous hyperboles. If they could not equal the ancient poets in point of genius, they were resolved to excel them in fiction, and apply to the wonder rather than the judgment of their readers. Accordingly they brought necromancy to their aid, and instead of supporting the character of their heroes, by dignity of sentiment and practice, distinguished them by their bodily strength, activity, and extravagance of behaviour. Although nothing could be more ludicrous and unnatural than the figures they drew, they did not want patrons and admirers; and the world actually began to be infected with the spirit of knight-errantry, when Cervantes, by an inimitable piece of ridicule, reformed the taste of mankind, representing chivalry in the right point of view, and converting romance to purposes far more useful and entertaining, by making it assume the sock, and point out the follies of ordinary life.</p>
            <p>
The same method has been practised by other Spanish and French authors, and by none more successfully than by Monsieur Le Sage, who, in his Adventures of Gil Blas, has described the knavery and foibles of life, with infinite humour and sagacity. - The following sheets I have modelled on his plan, taking me liberty, however, to differ from him in the execution, where I thought his particular situations were uncommon, extravagant, or peculiar to the country in which the scene is laid. - The disgraces of Gil Blas are, for the most part, such as rather excite mirth than compassion; he himself laughs at them; and his transitions from distress to happiness, or at least ease, are so sudden, that neither the reader has time to pity him, nor himself to be acquainted with affliction. This conduct, in my opinion, not only deviates from probability, but prevents that generous indignation which ought to animate the reader, against the sordid and vicious disposition of the world. </p>
            <p>
I have attempted to represent modest merit struggling with every difficulty to which a friendless orphan is exposed, from his own want of experience, as well as from the selfishness, envy, malice, and base indifference of mankind. - To secure a favourable prepossession, I have allowed him the advantages of birth and education, which in the series of his misfortunes will, I hope, engage the ingenuous more warmly in his behalf; and though I foresee, that some people will be offended at the mean scenes in which he is involved, I persuade myself that the judicious will not only perceive the necessity of describing those situations to which he must of course be confined, in his low estate, but also find entertainment in viewing those parts of life, where the humours and passions are undisguised by affectation, ceremony, or education; and the whimsical peculiarities of disposition appear as nature has implanted them.- But I believe I need not trouble myself in vindicating a practice authorized by the best writers in this way, some of whom I have already named.</p>
            <p>
Every intelligent reader will, at first sight, perceive I have not deviated from nature, in the facts, which are all true in the main, although the circumstances are altered and disguised, to avoid personal satire.</p>
            <p>
It now remains to give my reasons for making the chief personage of this work a North Briton; which are chiefly these: I could, at a small expense, bestow on him such education as I thought the dignity of his birth and character required, which could not possibly be obtained in England, by such slender means as the nature of my plan would afford. In the next place, I could represent simplicity of manners in a remote part of the kingdom, with more propriety than in any place near the capital; and lastly, the disposition of the Scots, addicted to travelling, justifies my conduct in deriving an adventurer from that country. </p>
            <p>
That the delicate reader may not be offended at the unmeaning oaths which proceed from the mouths of some persons in these memoirs, I beg leave to promise, that I imagined nothing could more effectually expose the absurdity of such miserable expletives, than a natural and verbal representation of the discourse in which they occur.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>